<!DOCTYPE ui:UiBinder SYSTEM "http://dl.google.com/gwt/DTD/xhtml.ent">
<ui:UiBinder xmlns:ui="urn:ui:com.google.gwt.uibinder">
	<ui:with field="mainRes" type="com.gmi.gwaswebapp.client.resources.MyResources" />
	
	<div class="{mainRes.style.help_section}" >
		<h1><a name="analysis">Analysis</a></h1>
		<p>
		The Analysis page is the main page in the GWAS-Web-App.<br /> 
		It contains most of the functionality and will be used most of the time. It consists of 4 distinct views:
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li><b>Phenotype-View</b>: information about the phenotypes</li>
			<li><b>Dataset-View</b>: information about the datasets</li>
			<li><b>Transformation-View</b>: information about the transformations</li>
			<li><b>Results-View</b>: GWAS results and plots</li>
		</ul>
		<p>
		The views are hierarchically structured starting with the Phenotype-View being the root view. Each Phenotype can contain multiple datasets.<br/>
		By default every uploaded phenotype has a <b>Fullset</b> dataset which contains all accession for which phenotype-values exists. <br/>
		Each dataset can have multiple transformations. By default every dataset has the <b>raw</b> transformation which are the untransformed phenotype-values. 
		Each transformation can have multiple GWAS-results. There are currently 3 different GWAS-methods (EMMAX,LM and KW).    
		</p>
		<h2><a name="analysis_navigation" id="analysis_navigation">Navigation</a></h2>
		<div id="navigation" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_container}">
			<div>
			<a href="#!helpPage;section=analysis" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_close_link}"><img src="{mainRes.close_button.getSafeUri.asString}" /></a>
			<a href="#navigation">
				<img src="/public/resources/screens/navigation.png" class="{mainRes.style.help_image}"></img>
			</a>
			<i>Figure: Navigation (click figure for fullscreen)</i>
			</div>
		</div>
		
		<div class="{mainRes.style.clearfix}"></div>
		<p>
		Navigation in the view is quite straightforward.<br></br>
		On the left side there is a navigation bar containing a tree which shows provides access to the above mentioned 4 views.<br></br>
		On the right side the corresponding view will be displayed. 
		<br></br>
		</p>
		<h2><a name="analysis_phenotypes" id="analysis_phenotypes">Phenotypes</a></h2>
		<p>
		The Phenotype-View consists of two different sub-views. By default (when clicking on Analysis) the phenotype-list view is loaded (see <a href="#navigation">Navigation-Figure</a>).<Br/>
		The phenotype-list view shows general information about all currently stored phenotypes and also contains two barcharts. One barchart visualizes the number of phenotype values and the other visualizes the number of datasets, transformations and GWAS-results contained in a phenotype.<br/>
		The user can also delete a specific phenotype by clicking on the delete button.<br></br>
		As soon as the user selects a specific phenotype from the navigation tree on the left side, the Phenotype-View is loaded (see figure below)
		</p>
		<div id="phenotype_view" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_container}">
			<div>
			<a href="#!helpPage;section=analysis" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_close_link}"><img src="{mainRes.close_button.getSafeUri.asString}" /></a>
			<a href="#phenotype_view">
				<img src="/public/resources/screens/phenotype_view.png" class="{mainRes.style.help_image}"></img>
			</a>
			<i>Figure: Phenotype-View (click figure for fullscreen)</i>
			</div>
		</div>
		<div class="{mainRes.style.clearfix}"></div>
		<p>
			In the top area of the phenotype-view general phenotype information are displayed.<br/>
			Below a list of all datasets in the specific phenotype are shown.<br/> 
			The <b>Geographic Distribution Map</b> for the selected dataset in that list is displayed further down.<br/> 
			By selecting another dataset from the dataset table this <b>Geographic Distribution Map</b> will get updated.
		</p>
		<p> The dataset table also allows to delete a dataset (with the exception of the default <b>Fullset</b>)<br/>
			By clicking on the <b>Subset</b> button it is possible to create a new dataset based on the selected dataset (more about that in the next section).
			In the bottom part of the view some statistics about the datasets contained in the phenotype are displayed. On the left side the number of accessions/values in each dataset is displayed and on the right side the number of transformations and different GWAS-results are visualized.  
		</p>
		<h2><a name="analysis_datasets" id="analysis_datasets">Datasets</a></h2>
		<p>
			By selecting a specific dataset from the left navigation tree or clicking on the <b>Subset</b> button the Dataset-View is loaded.<br/>
			The Dataset-View consists of different information-boxes:
		</p>
		<p>
			<ul>
				<li><b>Filter-Box</b>: This box allows to filter the accession-list. In Edit-Mode it is possible to change the dataset name and description.</li>
				<li><b>Accession-List</b>: This table shows all accessions which are currently forming the dataset. In Edit-Mode the accession-list is used to add and remove accessions from the dataset.</li>
				<li><b>Geographic Distribution Map</b>: Visualizes the geographic distribution of the dataset</li>
				<li><b>Google Map</b>: Shows the locations of all accessions in the dataset on a world map</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
			<div id="dataset_view" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_container}">
			<div>
			<a href="#!helpPage;section=analysis" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_close_link}"><img src="{mainRes.close_button.getSafeUri.asString}" /></a>
			<a href="#dataset_view">
				<img src="/public/resources/screens/create_subsets.png" class="{mainRes.style.help_image}"></img>
			</a>
			<i>Figure: Dataset-View (click figure for fullscreen)</i>
			</div>
		</div>
		<div class="{mainRes.style.clearfix}"></div>
			<p>
			In <b>Readonly mode</b> the user can filter/search the accession list.<br/>
			In <b>Edit mode</b> (either by editing a dataset or creating a new one) the user can remove or add accessions to the dataset.<br/>
			Only accessions from the fullset can be added or removed from the dataset. 
			The <b>Fullset CAN NOT</b> be deleted or edited.
			</p> 
			<p> 
			Removing or adding accessions to a dataset is down by clicking on the checkbox in the accession-list. Adding or removing multiple accessions can be done by pressing the <b>SHIFT</b> keyboard-button while clicking on the checkboxes.  
			</p>
			<h2><a name="transformations" id="analysis_transformations">Transformations</a></h2>
			<p>
				Selecting a transformation from one of the datasets will load the Transformation-View.<br/>
				The transformation view contains following information widgets: 
				<ul>
					<li><b>Transformation-list</b>: list with all transformations in the dataset</li>
					<li><b>Histogram</b>: histogram of the transformed phenotype-values</li>
					<li><b>Phenotype-Explorer</b>: motionchart of phenotype-values and accession information</li>
					<li><b>Results-list</b>: list of all GWAS-results for the currently selected transformation</li>
				</ul>
			</p> 
			<div id="transformation_view" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_container}">
			<div>
			<a href="#!helpPage;section=analysis" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_close_link}"><img src="{mainRes.close_button.getSafeUri.asString}" /></a>
			<a href="#transformation_view">
				<img src="/public/resources/screens/transformation_view.png" class="{mainRes.style.help_image}"></img>
			</a>
			<i>Figure: Transformation-View (click figure for fullscreen)</i>
			</div>
		</div>
		<div class="{mainRes.style.clearfix}"></div>
		<p>
		The transformation-list shows all transformations in the current selected dataset.<br/>
		Users can delete transformations, create new ones and also run one of the GWAS-method on a specific transformation.</p>
		<p>
		Below the histogram of the phenotype-values for the selected transformations is displayed.<br/>
		In case the user creates a new transformation, a preview-histogram for the desired transformation is shown in addition to the original histogram.<br/> 
		</p>
		<p>
		Further down the Phenotype-Explorer is shown.
		</p>
		<h3>Phenotype-Explorer</h3>
		<p>
		The phenotype explorer has two modes. First it can display a scatterplot/xy-plot of all accessions. The x- and y-axis can be set to longitude, latitude or phenotype. 
		Additional information ca be visualized by the size and the color of the circles (see <a href="#phenotype_explorer_scatter">figure</a> below).
		</p>
		<div id="phenotype_explorer_scatter" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_container}">
			<div>
			<a href="#!helpPage;section=analysis" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_close_link}"><img src="{mainRes.close_button.getSafeUri.asString}" /></a>
			<a href="#phenotype_explorer_scatter">
				<img src="/public/resources/screens/phenotype_explorer_scatter.png" class="{mainRes.style.help_image}"></img>
			</a>
			<i>Figure: Phenotype-Explorer Scatterchart (click figure for fullscreen)</i>
			</div>
			</div>
		<div class="{mainRes.style.clearfix}"></div>
		<p>
		The second mode is a barchart where the x-axis can be ordered by phenotype, longitude, latitude or alphabetically and the y-axis can bei the actual values. Again color can code another information (see <a href="#phenotype_explorer_bar">figure</a> below).
		</p>
		<div id="phenotype_explorer_bar" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_container}">
			<div>
			<a href="#!helpPage;section=analysis" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_close_link}"><img src="{mainRes.close_button.getSafeUri.asString}" /></a>
			<a href="#phenotype_explorer_bar">
				<img src="/public/resources/screens/phenotype_explorer_bar.png" class="{mainRes.style.help_image}"></img>
			</a>
			<i>Figure: Phenotype-Explorer Barchart (click figure for fullscreen)</i>
			</div>
			</div>
			<div class="{mainRes.style.clearfix}"></div>
			<h2><a name="results" id="analysis_results">Results</a></h2>
			<p>
			The Results-View displays the GWAS-result.<br/>
			It consists of a tab-panel with 2 main views:</p>
			<h3>GWAS-Plots</h3>
			<p>
			For each chromosome a scatterplot will be displayed showing the <b>top 10.0000 SNPs</b>.<br/>
			The x-axis measures the positions along the genome/chromosome and the y-axis displays the p-Value scale.<br/>
			Furthermore a <b>dashed</b> horizontal line visualizes the <b><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bonferroni_correction" target="_blank">bonferroni threshold</a></b>.<br/>
			In the top left corner there is a autofilled textbox which allows to search for a specific Arabidopsis Thaliana gene.<br/>
			If the user selects a gene it will be highlighted as a colored band in the corresponding scatterplot.<br/>
			By moving the mouse over a SNP the pValue and the position of the SNP will be displayed in the upper right corner of the scatterplot.<br/>
			Clicking on a SNP in the scatterplot opens a popup which allows the user to run a step-wise GWAS analysis with the selected SNP as a co-factor (<b>works only with EMMAX</b>)  
			
			</p>
			<div id="results_view_plots" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_container}">
			<div>
			<a href="#!helpPage;section=analysis" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_close_link}"><img src="{mainRes.close_button.getSafeUri.asString}" /></a>
			<a href="#results_view_plots">
				<img src="/public/resources/screens/results_view_plots.png" class="{mainRes.style.help_image}"></img>
			</a>
			<i>Figure: GWAS-plots (click figure for fullscreen)</i>
			</div>
			</div>
			<div class="{mainRes.style.clearfix}"></div>
			<p>
			Below each scatterplot an invisible <b>Geneviewer</b> is hidden which is displayed as soon as the user zooms into a region smaller than <b>1.5 Mb</b>.<br/>
			The user can zoom either vertically along the y-xis or horizontally along the x-axis.<br/>
			Zooming in the scatterplot is done by pressing and holding the left mouse button somewhere in the scatterplot (this defines the staring point) and and then dragging the mouse (while holding the left mouse button) to the endpoint of the zoomarea.<br/>
			A grey band visualizes the region  which the scatterplot will be zoomed into as soon as the user releases the left mouse-button. 
			Zooming out is done by double clicking somewhere into the scatterplot.</p>
			<p>
			The <b>Geneviewer</b> has two zoom levels.<br/>
			The first zooom level is between <b>1.5 Mb</b> and <b>100 kb</b> and the Geneviewer will display a simple gene model without any features (see <a href="#results_view_plots_zoom1">figure</a> below).<br></br>
			When the user moves the mouse over a gene a popup with information about the specific gene will be displayed.<br/>
			Furthermore moving the mouse over a SNP in the scatterplot will show a vertical line visualizing the position of the SNP in the Geneviewer and highlighting the gene in case the SNP lies on the gene.
			</p>
			<div id="results_view_plots_zoom1" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_container}">
			<div>
			<a href="#!helpPage;section=analysis" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_close_link}"><img src="{mainRes.close_button.getSafeUri.asString}" /></a>
			<a href="#results_view_plots_zoom1">
				<img src="/public/resources/screens/results_view_plots_zoom1.png" class="{mainRes.style.help_image}"></img>
			</a>
			<i>Figure: GWAS-plots and Geneviewer with simple gene model (click figure for fullscreen)</i>
			</div>
			</div>
			<div class="{mainRes.style.clearfix}"></div>
			<p>
			The second zoom level is displayed when the user zoomed into a region smaller than <b>1.5 Mb</b><br/>
			A more complex gene model will be displayed with gene-features (UTRs and exons).<br/>
			Moving the mouse over a SNP in the scatterplot will not only display which gene but also which gene feature was hit. 
			</p>
			<div id="results_view_plots_zoom2" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_container}">
			<div>
			<a href="#!helpPage;section=analysis" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_close_link}"><img src="{mainRes.close_button.getSafeUri.asString}" /></a>
			<a href="#results_view_plots_zoom2">
				<img src="/public/resources/screens/results_view_plots_zoom2.png" class="{mainRes.style.help_image}"></img>
			</a>
			<i>Figure: GWAS-plots and Geneviewer with complex gene model (click figure for fullscreen)</i>
			</div>
			</div>
			<div class="{mainRes.style.clearfix}"></div>
			<p>
			In cae of a step-wise GWAS result the scatterplots will also indicated which SNPs where used as co-factors in the model by drawing a vertical line to the corresponding SNP. 
			</p>
			<h2><a name="statistics">Statistics</a></h2>
			<p>
			The second view in the Results-View's tab-panel shows statisctics about the GWAS-results.<br/>
			This view is important for the step-wise GWAS results because it shows how some statistical properties change in each step of the step-wise GWAS analysis.<br/>
			This can help to decide when to stop including more co-factors in the GWAS analysis (see introduction for more information).<br/>  
			</p>
			<div id="results_view_statistics" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_container}">
			<div>
			<a href="#!helpPage;section=analysis" class="{mainRes.style.help_image_close_link}"><img src="{mainRes.close_button.getSafeUri.asString}" /></a>
			<a href="#results_view_statistics">
				<img src="/public/resources/screens/results_view_statistics.png" class="{mainRes.style.help_image}"></img>
			</a>
			<i>Figure: Statistics after 3 steps (click figure for fullscreen)</i>
			</div>
			</div>
			<div class="{mainRes.style.clearfix}"></div>
			<p>
			The Statistics view consists of a table with all the statistical indicators/properties at any given step.<br/>
			Futhermore there is a listbox which allows the users to select an indicator for visualization as a line-chart.  
			</p>
	</div>
</ui:UiBinder>